Okay, so today's דף daf is ט"ו. Tes Vav. We start from
the very bottom of י"ד עמוד ב', Yud Daled Amud Beis, אתו
אינהו, Atu Inhu, and the question on the table is that we
had said that treating hands as a שני לטומאה sheini l'tumah that
they can make תרומה trumah טמא tamei was from the גזירות gezeros
of בית שמאי Beis Shammai and בית הלל Beis Hillel of the
18 things, and the question is, is that really true? Because we
had another report that that actually—I think
we were a little further up, okay, up
to—oh I'm sorry, okay fine. Anyway, because we had an earlier report
that that was actually a תקנה takkanah of יוסי בן יועזר איש
צרידה Yosei ben Yoezer Ish Tzreidah and יוסי בן יוחנן איש—no, Yosei
ben Yochanan Ish I'm sorry, not them, excuse me, it was a
תקנה takkanah of שמאי Shammai and הלל Hillel themselves and not בית
שמאי Beis Shammai and בית הלל. Beis Hillel. So let's take a
look from that point of the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara
says וכי תימא, V'chee Teima,
we'll pick up from there. The end of the line of about
10 lines from the bottom of כ"ט, Chaf Tes, וכי תימא, V'chee
Teima,
and maybe you want to say שמאי וסיעתו, Shammai v'siyato, הלל וסיעתו,
Hillel v'siyato, that when we say it was בית שמאי Beis Shammai
and בית הלל Beis Hillel and in another version it says שמאי
Shammai and הלל, Hillel, that they really don't disagree. That שמאי Shammai
and הלל Hillel means שמאי Shammai and his college and his בית
מדרש Beis Medrash and הלל Hillel his בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. So
they were part of the י"ח דבר Yud Ches Davar that can't
be. והאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, v'ha'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, י"ח
דבר גזרו ובי"ח נחלקו, Yud Ches Davar gazru b'Yud Ches nechelku,
that the 18 things they ruled on and there were 18 things
that they debated on. Presumably, I'll discuss the ירושלמי Yerushalmi in a
minute, but the בבלי Bavli seems to understand that these were the
same 18. And therefore what it's saying is that the same 18
that were part of the י"ח דבר Yud Ches Davar that they
agreed upon originally had been things they debated. Okay, so why is
that a problem? ואילו הלל ושמאי לא נחלקו אלא בשלשה מקומות, V'eelu
Hillel v'Shammai lo nechelku ela b'shlosha mekomos,
we know that הלל Hillel and שמאי Shammai only disagreed on three
areas and ידים Yadayim wasn't one of them. So when we say
הלל Hillel and שמאי Shammai were מתקן mtakkein ידים, Yadayim, what we
mean then was it could not have been the י"ח דבר Yud
Ches Davar because י"ח דבר Yud Ches Davar were things which were
debated and הלל Hillel and שמאי Shammai never debated the טומאה tumah
of ידים. Yadayim. So it can't be that. That's not—you cannot try
to conflate the two. וכי תימא, V'chee Teima, so now let's try
another way of reconciling it. אתו אינהו גזרו לתלות, Atu inhu gazru
litlos,
maybe it was degrees to which the גזירה gezeirah was passed. And
הלל Hillel and שמאי Shammai said that if your hands touch תרומה,
trumah, you're תולה, toleh, which means you don't treat it as totally
טמא tamei because really it's only דרבנן. d'rabbanan. So we're only going
to—we're not going to go so far, so we're going to say
don't eat it but don't burn it. Wait till it becomes invalid
and then you can go ahead and use it. Hold on one
sec, we might actually have this up. So then you can go
ahead and use it.
I'm sorry, you have to wait for it to become invalid and
then you can go ahead and burn it. And so that was
one stage that we weren't so strict, we recognized sort of that
it was only דרבנן d'rabbanan and we didn't go so far.
Okay, where were we? ואתו תלמידיהו וגזרו לשרוף, v'asu talmideihu v'gazru lisfrof,
and then their students came and they made it go to the
very end, they actually said that it was going to—okay, I see
what I did wrong, fine for tomorrow—and they actually said that they
were going to have to burn it. So you were really going
to treat it as really טמא. tamei. So maybe that's the way
it worked in two degrees. והאמר אילפא, V'ha'amar Ilfa, you can't say
that, says אילפא, Ilfa, ידים תחלת גזירתן לשריפה, Yadayim techilas gzeirasom l'sreifah,
that from the very outset when they made this תקנה, takkanah, they
said that you would burn if your hands touched something,
then you'd have to burn, if your hands touch תרומה, trumah, you'd
have to burn the תרומה. trumah. So you cannot say there were
two stages. In שמאי Shammai and הלל Hillel they said don't eat
the תרומה, trumah, don't burn it, and the בית שמאי Beis Shammai
and בית הלל Beis Hillel said actually burn it, because we have
a teaching that from the very beginning they were so strict by
hands that when they touch תרומה, trumah, you would burn the תרומה.
trumah. So how do you explain therefore these two stages? אלא הכי
קאמר אתו אינהו גזרו ולא קיבלו מנייהו, Ela hachi ka'amar: Atu inhu
gazru v'lo kiblu minaihu,
they came and they attempted to say שמאי Shammai and הלל Hillel
that there was ידים Yadayim were טמא tamei and it wasn't accepted.
And one of the principles about a תקנה takkanah is that if
it's not accepted by כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, אין גוזרין גזירה על
הצבור אלא אם כן רוב צבור יכולין לעמוד בה, ein gozrin gezeirah
ela im ken rov hatzibbur yachol la'amod bah, is that you're not
supposed to make the גזירה. gezeirah. Let's say you went ahead and
you made the גזירה, gezeirah, it's not binding unless it's accepted by
כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. It's like the flip side of the same
coin. Anyway, so if it's not accepted by כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael,
it does not become binding. So they tried but it didn't succeed.
ואתו תלמידיהו גזרו וקיבלו מנייהו, v'asu talmideihu gazru v'kiblu minaihu, okay,
and then their students came and at that stage people were more
receptive to it and therefore it got accepted. So that's an interesting
way of reconciling it also, that their students and the houses had
more influence but maybe the society had shifted this way. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says
ואכתי שלמה גזר, V'akati Shlomo gazar, one minute, I still can't accept
that it was שמאי Shammai and הלל Hillel or בית שמאי Beis
Shammai and בית הלל. Beis Hillel. We have another teaching that שלמה
Shlomo was the one who established טומאת ידים. tumas Yadayim. דאמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל, D'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, בשעה שתיקן שלמה עירובין
ונטילת ידים. b'sha'ah she'tikein Shlomo eruvin v'netilas yadayim. And
there's a tradition that שלמה *Shlomo* made these two rabbinic תקנות takkanos.
*takkanot*, very interesting projecting this all the way back to שלמה *Shlomo*.
שלמה המלך *Shlomo HaMelech*, exactly. Not to be confused with any other
שלמה *Shlomo*. And that was עירובין *eruvin*, that if you have like
these courtyards and you wanted to carry in it, that you would
make a, you know, that you would have to sort of combine
together and make some type of a unified courtyard, even though it
was a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. *reshus hayachid*. And that you would
have to wash your hands, נטילת ידים yadayim, *netilas yadayim*. Very interesting
why we assume these two of all others of all possible things.
Anyway, when שלמה *Shlomo* went ahead and made this תקנה takanah *takkanah*,
meaning that you wash your hands before eating bread, which is based
on the idea of that your hands are a שני לטומאה sheni
letumah, *sheni l'tumah* and would make תרומה terumah טמאה *terumah tamei*. And
because it would make תרומה terumah טמאה *terumah tamei*, and therefore eating
bread evokes the eating of כהנים Kohanim *kohanim* of תרומה terumah. *terumah*.
You realize it's a couple degrees removed. First you say your hands
are טמא tamei. *tamei* and they make תרומה terumah טמאה *terumah tamei*.
Then you say anytime you eat bread it's like you're eating תרומה
terumah *terumah* and therefore everybody who eats bread has to wash their
hands. Anyway, and we're attributing all of this to שלמה *Shlomo*. And
when he did this, יצתה בת קול *yatzta bas kol* and said,
בני אם חכם לבך ישמח לבי גם אני *beni im hacham libecha
yismach libi gam ani*, my son, if your heart is wise, my
heart will also be glad. Meaning it was something you did on
your own. It was rabbinic, not biblical, but it's a good idea,
I agree with you, you know, you've got my approval. חכם בני
ושמח לבי ואשיבה חרפי דבר *hacham beni v'samach libi v'ashiva chorfi davar*.
My son is wise and my heart is glad and I will
respond to those who blaspheme
me a matter. So maybe that's דוד *Dovid* talking, not God. Anyway,
so anyway,
God was very happy and שלמה *Shlomo* did the תקנה takanah *takkanah*.
So therefore it's not הלל Hillel *Hillel* and שמאי Shammai *Shammai*. So
how do you reconcile that teaching? So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: אמר שלמה גזר לקדשים *amar Shlomo gazar l'kodshim*.
שלמה *Shlomo* said that your hands are טמא tamei *tamei* only when
you touch קדשים *kodshim*. ואתו אינהו וגזרו אף אתרומה *v'atu inhu v'gazru
af aterumah*. And they said even when you touch תרומה terumah, *terumah*.
Now that's interesting because if you only said it for קדשים *kodshim*,
which is a lower level טומאה tumah. *tumah*, you know, a טומאה
tumah *tumah* that can only impact קדשים *kodshim* and not תרומה terumah,
*terumah*, like a שלישי *shelishi*, then the נטילת ידים *netilas yadayim* would
not be when I assume a normal person eats bread because what
would eating bread do to evoke the idea of קדשים *kodshim*? I
mean, if anything, it wouldn't be bread, it would be that eating
meat, you know. So it seems like there now we're saying, I
understand it's possible. Anyway, it seems like we're now saying that when
he says נטילת ידים *netilas yadayim*, he means נטילת ידים *netilas yadayim*
of כהנים *kohanim* who are going to eat קדשים *kodshim* or of
somebody who brought a קרבן korban *korban* to eat his קדשים *kodshim*,
but not the נטילת ידים *netilas yadayim* we have nowadays. At least
the way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is reframing this idea.
And then שמאי Shammai, *Shammai* did it and it didn't hold, and
then the תלמידים *talmidim* did it and it did
hold even for תרומה terumah. *terumah*. Exactly. Okay, anyway. Now the גמרא
Gemara... *Gemara* says: גופא *gufa*. Let's go back and look at that
earlier statement. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל *amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel*,
י"ח גזרו וי"ח נחלקו *yud ches gazru v'yud ches necheleku*. They gave
an edict on eighteen and on eighteen they debated. And again, from
the earlier גמרא Gemara *Gemara* it sounds like they're saying the eighteen
that eventually were the י"ח דבר *yud ches davar* were originally things
that they had debated. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: והא תניא
הושוו *ve-ha tanya hushvu*. One minute, don't we say that they sort
of were consensus about it? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: בו
ביום נחלקו ולמחר הושוו *bo bayom necheleku u-le-machar hushvu*. They debated that
day and then they were a consensus. So it's not exactly clear.
You have these three statements: they debated, they made a גזירה gezeira,
*gezeirah*, and they were and, you know, and there was a consensus.
Sounds like what it's saying is that there had been a long-standing
debate. Then they, בית שמאי Beis Shammai *Beis Shammai* outruled בית הלל
Beis Hillel *Beis Hillel* and they took a vote and they won.
So they גזרו *gazru*. And then by the next day הלל Hillel
*Hillel* said, well, as long as you guys already won, we concede.
And then it was הושוו *hushvu*.
So anyway, that seems to be what the בבלי *Bavli* is saying.
The ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* actually says that there were three different sets of
eighteen. There were eighteen things that
they had been a debate and that בית שמאי Shammai *Beis Shammai*
won out and בית הלל Beit Hillel, *Beis Hillel* when they were
visiting, you know, חנניה בן חזקיה בן גוריון *Hananya ben Chizkiya ben
Guryon*. Anyway, whoever it was. Anyway, בן גורון *Ben Goron*. Whoever. Anyway,
בן גורן *Ben Goran*. Anyway, חנניה בן חזקיה בן גרון *Hananya ben
Chizkiya ben Garon*. Excuse me. Anyway, so that there were eighteen things
that they actually were fighting about. They took a vote. They won
out. That was the י"ח גזרו *yud ches gazru*.
Then there were eighteen things that were הושוו *hushvu*, that they never
debated. There was always a consensus. Okay. And then there were י"ח
*yud ches* that were נחלקו *necheleku*, which means remained a matter of
debate. And actually, the רמב"ם *Rambam* gives an interesting gloss on this.
The רמב"ם *Rambam* says, because obviously they debated more than eighteen things.
But the way the רמב"ם *Rambam* says it is, when they were
taking that vote in the, in the,
you know, over there in the story of חנניה בן חזקיה בן
גרון *Hananya ben Chizkiya ben Garon*, so
eighteen things they knew they could win on. So they voted on
those. That was the י"ח גזרו *yud ches gazru*. Then there were
eighteen things which they weren't so sure. They thought maybe one of
their house members of their house would switch sides. So there those
eighteen they chose not to take a vote on because שמאי Shammai
*Shammai* didn't know which way it would go. And therefore those eighteen
remained a matter of debate. And the רמב"ם *Rambam* actually says that
those are the eighteen the next משניות *Mishnayos* we're going to have
till the end of the second, till the end of the first
פרק *perek* are
going to
be. Wait. I want to tell you all three sets of the
רמב״ם *Rambam* has three sets of 18 following the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*. Debates
that are going to follow in the rest of the משניות *Mishnayos*
till the end of the פרק *Perek* and that they remained debates
and they chose not to vote. The 18 that preceded, the רמב״ם
*Rambam* counts 18 from the בעל הבית *Baal habayis* and the עני
*Ani* and carrying before שבת *Shabbos* and sitting down to get a
haircut, those were 18 that they were always a consensus on, and
what we're listing now in the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*, all these things
about שני לטומאה sheni letumah *Sheni l'tumah*, all these טומאה וטהרה tumah
vetaharah *Tumah v'taharah* things, those are 18 that they debated but then
שמאי Shammai *Shammai* won out and they were גזרו *Guzru*. So according
to the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* there were three sets and the רמב״ם *Rambam*
identifies the three sets. Consensus, what preceded this משנה Mishnah. *Mishna*, remained
a debate what followed the משנה Mishna, *Mishna*, and the things that
were debated and שמאי Shammai. *Shammai* won the vote is what we're
talking about in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* which are all these things
about טומאה וטהרה tumah vetaharah. *Tumah v'taharah*. You had a question, Shaya?
You had a whole bunch of rabbis together and they managed to
decide on 18 things? Well if they only decide,
oh you mean the consensus things. The בבלי *Bavli* interestingly doesn't assume
there was a consensus. The בבלי *Bavli* conflates it all into one
big debate.
Yeah, I must tell you, I'm glad you said that because I
was going to ask the question because if it really would have
been that there was a מחלוקת *Machlokes* and then there's a גזירה
gezeira *Gezeirah*, it should have been נחלקו י״ח גזרו *Nichleku yud ches
guzru*. The order here is י״ח גזרו *Yud ches guzru*.
I understand. So the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* has a much better read. The
ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* sees these as three separate groups. The בבלי *Bavli* tries
to conflate it all. Yeah, the order is... I understand. Right, yeah.
Rifka had step- בת קול *Bat Kol*, they didn't really mean to
debate, it's just like a...
Right, right.
Just wanted to decide something that they had no... exactly... well... no
textual, there's nothing clear they say
okay with the בת קול *Bat Kol*.
Well, yeah, I would also say that... right, I would also say
that the way we understand בת קול *Bat Kol* as a heavenly
voice is talking about the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*, and the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* בת
קול *Bat Kol* more means like a... you know, a report went
out, meaning like there, you know, that it was that... it's more
metaphoric- a, it's metaphoric, but it's not even metaphoric as a heavenly
voice, it more means like, you know, gossip people talking about it.
Yeah, everybody was- there was a widespread acceptance of this thing. Word
got around. I understand.
Like שמואל *Shmuel* now.
Yeah, I understand, yeah. Absolutely, absolutely. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
continues. גופא *Gufa*. אמר רב הונא *Amar Rav Huna*, בג׳ מקומות נחלקו
שמאי Shammai, והלל *B'gimmel mekomos nechleku Shammai v'Hillel*. Now going back to
שמאי Shammai. *Shammai* and הלל Hillel *Hillel* who debated only three things
before we return to בית שמאי Shammai. *Beit Shammai* and בית הלל
Beit Hillel. *Beit Hillel* and the 18 things. ששמאי אומר omer, *Sheshammai
omer*, here are the three- here are the three things. מקב חלה
challah. *Mikav challah*. When you have to take חלה challah, *challah*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, you know, ראשית עריסותיכם *Reishis arisoseichem*, your
kneading troughs, and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* understands that means the- the
same way that you had the- the amount of bread that you
had in the מדבר midbar, *Midbar*, the amount of the מן *Man*,
and the מן *Man* was- you know, the עומר omer לגלגלת *Omer
l'gulgoles* was עשירית האיפה asirit ha-eiphah. *Asiris ha'eifah*, a tenth of an
איפה eiphah. *Eifah*. An איפה eiphah. *Eifah* is
72 קבים *Kavs*. So- I'm sorry, not 72 קבים *Kavs*, 72 לוגים
*Logs*. Let me just double check this, to- I'm getting a little
confused. Yes, 72 לוגים *Logs*. So a tenth of that is 7.2
לוג log. *Log*. Okay. Now, there are six לוג log. *Log* in
a קב kav. *Kav*. So שמאי Shammai *Shammai* will- I'm not going
to tell you how he does the math, but he does a
tenth which is more like an eleventh, don't worry- don't worry we
got it right now, a tenth, you know, מלגיו *Milgav*, מלבר *Milbar*,
there's different ways of doing rabbinic math. Anyway, so from that- from
72 he gets actually down to six. Okay, it's more like an
eleventh for him. So if you have- I'm- so I'm- he gets
down to six, meaning not 7.2 but six. Six לוג log *Log*
is a קב kav. *Kav*. So he says you take a קב
kav. *Kav* of חלה challah. *Challah*. והלל אומר *V'Hillel omer*, one minute,
did I do that right? One minute...
I think one minute.
Okay. You know, I'm not sure about that. Let- let's hold on.
So anyway, so שמאי Shammai... *Shammai* says it's a קב kav. *Kav*
of- חלה *Challah*'s from a קב kav *Kav*. הלל אומר Hillel omer,
מקביים *Hillel omer mikabbayim*, a קב kav, *Kav* and- two קבים *Kavs*
of flour for חלה *Challah*. וחכמים אומרים Vachachamim omrim, *Vachachamim omrim*, לא
כדברי זה ולא כדברי זה Lo k'divrei zeh v'lo k'divrei zeh, *Lo
kidivrei zeh v'lo kidivrei zeh*, it's not like הלל Hillel *Hillel*, not
like שמאי Shammai *Shammai*, אלא Ela, קב kav, ומחצה חייב בחלה *Ela
kav v'mechtzah chayav bachallah*, a קב kav *Kav* and a half is
חייב *Chayav* in חלה *Challah*. So here, let me just- do this
math again, one minute. Oh, okay, yeah, that was my mistake. Excuse
me,
one minute.
One minute. One minute.
Right, right, okay, I'm sorry I made a mistake. A קב kav
*Kav* is four לוג log. *Log*. So let me start with
the חכמים chachamim *Chachamim* and then we can work back to הלל
Hillel *Hillel* and שמאי Shammai *Shammai*. Okay. So according to the חכמים
chachamim *Chachamim* was not six לוג log, *Log*, I mean it's eight.
Okay. So basically here's what you've got.
You've got seventy-two לוג log is an איפה. Okay. The עומר omer.
is seven point two לוג. log עשירית האיפה.
That's your עומר. omer.
That's your עומר. One tenth of an איפה. Okay. 7.2 לוג. log.
Now, here it is: four לוג log equals a קב. kav. Okay?
So 7.2 לוג. log, Now, the thing is that 7.2 in the
מדבר, midbar there was a conversion of of the of the what
do you call it of the measures so that what used to
be what used to be six in the מדבר became five, six
קבין מדבריות, kavim midbariot, six in the time of the תורה Torah
was five in the time of חז"ל, Chazal, five ירושלמיות. Yerushalmiot. So
therefore the way you sort of get so what you do is
you multiply by five-sixths. Is that right?
Yes, by five-sixths in order to do the conversion. So you have
six לוג, log. if you're going to multiply by five-sixths, six לוג
log would become five. That was the basic conversion. What used to
be six became five. Okay? Is that somewhat clear? They made them
bigger. So like the אמה בת ששה טפחים מדבר. amah bat shisha
tfechim midbar. Then you're left with 1.2, then you're left with is
what, which is
six-fifths, right? Because six-fifths is 1.2. Like the seven לוג log. is
six and that's 1.2, right? 6 plus 1.2 is 7.2 לוג. log
Okay? Which is six-fifths times five-sixths equals one. So this 7.2 לוג
log? became six לוג ירושלמי. log Yerushalmi. Okay?
Is that somewhat clear? That's the conversion. So the new לוג, log,
the 7.2 became six, which is one and a half קב. kav,
Okay? So that's how the חכמים chachamim get one and a half
קב. kav,
הלל Hillel and שמאי Shammai. do the math a little bit differently.
I said it a little bit incorrectly before, but anyway, that's how
the חכמים chachamim's get one and a half קב. kav, Okay? So
that's why we say one and a half קב kav. for חלה.
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi okay, so that's what the חכמים Chachamim says.
משהגדילו המדות, mishehigdilu hamiddot,
after that conversion there was yet another conversion and they, you know,
and what had been, you know, and the same thing contained more
than it used to. So אמרו, amru, חמשה רבעים קמח חייב בחלה,
chamisha reva'im kemach chayav bechallah, that it is not one and a
half קבין, kavin, it is one and a quarter קבין kavin now,
I mean one and a quarter קבין. kavin. So now it had
because of the new conversion factor, five. ביצה ומחצה? beitzah u-mechitzah? Exactly.
Okay. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi אומר, now רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says:
ה' פטורים, hei peturim,
five exactly are exempt. ה' ועוד חייבים. hei va-od chayavim. So he
basically agrees, yes, it's five קב, kav, but it's five plus a
tiny bit, not exactly five. Why? So רש"י Rashi says it's because
he thinks קבין kavin are ultimately made up of a measure of
eggs, and his measure of eggs are a little bit bigger than
the חכמים's Chachamim measures of eggs. That's what he says. תוספות Tosafot
says a slightly different explanation, which is תוספות Tosafot says because he
agrees that the idea is five קב, kav but he just says
there has to be five קב left after you take חלה, not
that you start with five קב but you're left with five קב.
And therefore he says that's why you get that, yes, I agree
that it started six קב, it became five קב, but you have
to be left with five קב, so you need five plus a
little bit. Right, and you could just take a משהו, mashu, so
it's five plus a little bit. Anyway, that's one debate of הלל
Hillel and שמאי, how much for חלה. ואידך, ve-idach, what's the other
debate? הלל Hillel אומר, מלא הין מים שאובים פוסלים את המקוה, melo
hin mayim she'uvim poslin et ha-mikvah, a full הין hin of drawn
water invalidates a מקוה. mikvah. Okay? So a הין hin is twelve
לוג. log. A לוג log, is a רביעית revi'it that we have
for קידוש Kiddush and it's about three and a half ounces is
a רביעית revi'it of a לוג. log So a לוג is about,
you know, 14 ounces. So a הין hin is 12 of those,
what's that, 140, 28, 168 ounces. What's the normal bottle of soda?
Like one of those two liters, that's like 64 ounces or so?
Yes, 64 to 64.
Okay, so basically about a little more than two liters, you know,
two two-liter bottles. That what he says, that amount of water, drawn
water, invalidates a מקוה. mikvah. If you have a full forty סאה
se'ah on a מקוה, mikvah, then you could add drawn water, and
most of our מקוואות mikva'ot are made that way, that you have
the בור bor that has the rainwater, it's connected through a hole
to a בור bor that has water that you fill up from
the sink and that you constantly, not sink, whatever, the pipes, and
then you constantly have to change it and keep it clean. Once
you have forty סאה se'ah you're okay. But if before you had
the forty סאה, se'ah,
drawn water was in the בור bor and then rainwater came in
on top, the מקוה mikvah is invalid. How much drawn water? So
he says a full הין, hin, which is, as I said, about,
you know, two two-liter bottles. Okay, that's what he says.
שחייב אדם לומר בלשון רבו, she-chayav adam lomar bilshon rabbo, and you
have to say it the way you heard it from your רבי.
rebbe. Now what does that mean? So רש"י Rashi says because the
word הין hin is a biblical term, not a rabbinic term. I'll
get back in a minute and tell you what the גר"א Gra
says. The גר"א Gra has a nice reading of this. שמאי אומר,
Shammai omer, תשעה קבין. tisha kavin. So שמאי says it's nine קב.
Now, we just said a קב, so a תשעה קבין tisha kavin
is how many לוג? We said a קב is four לוג, so...
36. So Shammai basically said three times that amount. Very lenient, right?
According to Shammai we done six two-liter bottles of drawn water to
invalidate the מקווה. mikveh. Much more lenient than Hillel. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim
omrim, the sages say. So last time the sages were midpoint between
Shammai and Hillel. Here they are much stricter than both of them.
לא כדברי זה ולא כדברי זה, Lo k'divrei zeh v'lo k'divrei zeh,
not like either opinion, עד שבאו שני גרדיים משער האשפות שבירושלים, ad
shebau shnei gardiim misha'ar haashpot shebi-Yerushalayim, two weavers came from the Dung
Gate in Jerusalem והעידו משום שמעיה ואבטליון v'heidu mishum Shemaya v'Avtalyon and
they testified in the name of Shemaya and Avtalyon ששלשה לוגין מים
שאובין פוסלין את המקוה, sheshloshah lugin mayim sheuvin poslin et hamikveh, just
three לוג. So a quarter of what Hillel said. Like just three
לוג, which
is...
what do the חכמים Chachamim say? That's what they... well they וקיימו
חכמים את דבריהם v'kiyemu chachamim et divreihem and they backed that position.
Now right. So now this is important. The reason it mentions these
weavers is because the Gemara says, you know, weaving was considered to
be a very looked down upon profession. And to show you the
phrase the Gemara says לעולם לא ימנע אדם עצמו מבית המדרש. le'olam
lo yimna adam atzmo mibeit hamidrash. Nobody should ever stay out of
the study hall. You know, even somebody that feels like oh, I'm
not one of the sages, I'm not such a big תלמיד חכם.
talmid chacham. You remember we had these themes before about like whether
you keep people out or you get everybody in. And about how
they taught עדיות Eduyot when they decided to welcome everybody in. Right?
That's when they taught עדיות, Eduyot, because they were able to get
all these testimonies from people that had previously been excluded. So here
are two people you would never think they would have anything to
contribute and they had testimony from שמעיה ואבטליון. Shemaya v'Avtalyon. And the
חכמים chachamim backed their position and that leads to a very... it's
much more stringent that even three לוג of water invalidates, of drawn
water can invalidate the מקווה mikveh at the beginning. Now I want
to say something about this. It's very interesting because Hillel explicitly references
חייב אדם לומר בלשון רבו. chayav adam lomar bilshon rabo. Who is
who is Hillel's רבי? Rebbe? שמעיה ואבטליון. Shemaya v'Avtalyon. So listen to
that. Hillel is basically saying, and now you understand the power whatever
he's referring to of why he's using the exact language. The power
is he's saying I am directly quoting what I heard from my
רבנים. Rabbanim. And nevertheless we're giving weight to the testimony of these
two weavers who heard it from שמעיה ואבטליון Shemaya v'Avtalyon over Hillel's
statement. Why? Now what does that mean? Does that mean that we
believe... you know, first of all, there often are debates about who
heard... you know, people misrecollecting what they heard. But you would think
that the bias would be to go by Hillel than these two
anonymous people. Nevertheless they back... now it doesn't say why. I don't...
you know, a priori probably they wouldn't, but maybe for the חכמים
that position made more sense. It was more consistent with what they
had their traditions or what they had understood or it made sense
to them more. You know, I don't think a priori we would
have gone by the weavers over Hillel. But for whatever reason here
it seemed to make more sense to trust them more at least
in this case to believe that this was the more authentic teaching.
And it's very powerful especially if Hillel's not saying it as his
own opinion but he's actually claiming to quote לשון רבו. lishon rabo.
Now the גר"א Gra has an interesting explanation about what לשון רבו
lishon rabo means. The גר"א Gra says the problem isn't that he
said הין. hin. It's that he said מלא הין. mlo hin. Why
say מלא הין? mlo hin? Just say הין hin מים שאובין פוסלין
את המקוה. mayim sheuvin poslin et hamikveh. So he says שמעיה ואבטליון
Shemaya v'Avtalyon said מלא הין. mlo hin. Why? Because the גר"א Gra
says they were גרים geirim and therefore they had a hard time
pronouncing the ה hei which was guttural. We don't pronounce the ה
hei guttural, but the ה hei is really more guttural. So if
they were to say הין hin like as a guttural it wouldn't...
it would have sounded more like אין, in, אין, ein, אין מים
שאובין פוסלין את המקוה. ein mayim sheuvin poslin et hamikveh. So in
order that it wouldn't have been misunderstood, they said מלא הין, mlo
hin, so there couldn't have been misunderstood. Now Hillel could have said
הין, hin, he would have been understood, but he kept the phrase
מלא הין mlo hin because חייב אדם לומר בלשון רבו. chayav adam
lomar bilshon rabo. So that's the an explanation the גר"א Gra gives,
which I thought was very nice. Anyway, so that's the second debate.
והאידך, V'haidach, and the third debate, שמאי
אומר כל הנשים דיין שעתן Shammai omer kol hanashim dayan sha'atan והלל
אומרים מפקידה לפקידה. v'Hillel omrim mipkidah lipkidah. You might remember this from
נדה. Niddah. Shammai said any woman who finds a stain you can
assume the stain occurred just now and anything they touched before of
תרומה terumah or any other thing they might have touched we assume
is טהור. tahor. Hillel says no, we have to be concerned... again
Hillel here is more strict than Shammai. Quite interesting. Two out of
these three Hillel is more strict, exactly. Anyway, so... so Hillel says
no, you go all the way back מפקידה לפקידה mipkidah lipkidah until
the last time she checked. Until... if she checked three days ago
and she wasn't bleeding and now she finds a stain, for the
last three days she has to be concerned that she might have
been bleeding and anything she touched is considered
טמא. tamei וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim omrim, and the sages again come in,
ואפילו ימים הרבה, va'afilu yamim harbeh, even for a very long time.
וחכמים Vechachamim אומרים, the sages come in now with a compromise position.
לא lo, כדברי זה ולא כדברי זה, not like this one, not
like that one, אלא מעת לעת ממעט על יד מפקידה לפקידה ומפקידה
לפקידה ממעט על יד מעת לעת. ela me'et le'et mema'et al yad
mipkidah lipkidah umipkidah lipkidah mema'et al yad me'et le'et. 24 hours limits
the last time you checked and the last time you checked limits
24 hours. Meaning the lesser of the two. So if last time
you checked was three days ago we're not going to make you
טמא tamei retroactively more than 24 hours. If however the last time
you checked was five hours ago you're only טמא tamei? retroactively till
five hours ago. So you are טמא tamei backward until the earlier
of 24 hours or the last time you checked and that's the
way we rule. So now the Gemara says ותו ליכא, V'tu leika,
you're telling me there's no other... cases הלל Hillel and שמאי debated?
ואיכא v'ika how about the case הלל אומר לסמוך ושמאי אומר שלא
לסמוך? Hillel omer lismoch v'Shammai omer shelo lismoch? הלל Hillel says there's
a whole debate about whether you can bring נדרים ונדבות nedarim u'nedavos
on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Can you bring a קרבן that is
a שלמים shelamim that you're going to eat the meat of? Can
you bring it on יום טוב? Yom Tov? On the one hand,
you're שחיטה shechting it and you'll eat from it and you're allowed
to שחט shecht and eat meat on יום טוב. Yom Tov. On
the other hand, you know that's the... you're not eating all of
it and some of it is going to the מזבח mizbeach and
it's primary... sort of
primarily offered to God and then afterwards you're entitled to eat from
it. So are you allowed to bring נדרים ונדבות nedarim u'nedavos on
יום טוב Yom Tov is question number one. And question number two
is are you allowed to do סמיכה semicha on it when you
do bring it? And this is a long-standing debate. It's like one
of the things that was debated all the way back to the
זוגות... Zugos... like the very even pre-rabbinic period... you know the very
beginnings of the rabbinic period all the way down for like a
hundred and fifty years this was debated and every... you know... and
הלל Hillel and שמאי also were part of this debate. הלל אומר
לסמוך, Hillel omer lismoch, you can do סמיכה, semicha, ושמאי אומר שלא
לסמוך, v'Shammai omer shelo lismoch, not. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
כי קאמר רב הונא היכא דליכא פלוגתא דרבוותא. ki ka'amar Rav Huna
heicha d'leika plukta d'revusa. When... by the way... when are we saying
that they debated three times? It's when there weren't other people that
were part of the debates. היכא דליכא... heicha d'leika... היכא דאיכא heicha
d'ika but here...
but here...
you know they're just part of a long-standing debate. It's not a
unique debate of הלל Hillel and שמאי. It's not specific to them.
Okay so that's not counted. One minute but there's another case where
they debate. By the way the fact that we can mention only
three is... should be startling because we're so used to the idea
of הלל Hillel and שמאי, בית הלל Beit Hillel. and בית שמאי
debating everything, we assume the same is true about הלל Hillel. and
שמאי. But the reality is is that we have very few teachings
of הלל Hillel, and שמאי. I mean we have some in פרקי
אבות Pirkei Avos but you know in terms of halakhic teachings very
few and very few debates of הלל Hillel and שמאי and here
the גמרא Gemara is really... it has three, it suggested one more
and has one final one. Okay so let's take a look at
the one final one. ואיכא הבוצר לגת. v'ika habotzer legat. If you
are harvesting grapes that you are going to press to make into
wine. שמאי אומר הוכשר. Shammai omer huchshar. שמאי... and then what happens
is is that the grapes... grapes are in your basket and some
of the grape juice comes out. So is that liquid, right, considered
for grapes to be fit to become טמא? tamei. הוכשר, huchshar, made
susceptible... they have to come in contact with liquid but only if
you want the liquid. So here what is the story? You don't
really want the liquid to come out, you want it to save
its liquid till you get it into the vat. But...
and especially if it's a type of a basket that they would
often use that would have like holes in it, like a weaved
basket, so grape juice would drip out. But שמאי says nevertheless I'm
going to say treat it as if you wanted that juice because
there are times that you'll harvest with baskets that are plastered and
the juice will be contained and then you'll want the juice and
therefore I am going to say that the grapes become susceptible. והלל
אומר לא הוכשר. v'Hillel omer lo huchshar. It is not. So the
גמרא... Gemara so oh that's another debate. So it says no. בר
מינייהו דההיא. bar minei de'hahu. Don't count that one. That's not included.
דהתם קא שתיק ליה הלל לשמאי. dehasam kashatik lei Hillel leShammai. There
records שמאי's arguments and it says הלל Hillel. was silent, which means
he conceded. So since הלל Hillel conceded it doesn't count as one
of the debates. We're talking about a standing debate, not a debate
that was ultimately conceded.
A standing debate that's only between the two of them and not...
Right exactly.
But as an ongoing... exactly.
Okay so that is the הלל Hillel. and שמאי. Now of course
again we're... before we get back to the eighteen things which we
had listed we now have you know we're now looking a little
backwards because in discussing this issue about who was the first one
we quoted this ברייתא Braisa that said that you know early תקנות.
takkanos. So now we're going to go look back at the... at
those early תקנות. takanos, יוסי בן יועזר איש צרידה ויוסי בן יוחנן
איש ירושלים, Yosei ben Yoezer ish Tzereda v'Yosei ben Yochanan ish Yerushalayim,
again two... two you know תנאים Tannaim that we know really only
from פרקי אבות. Pirkei Avos. גזרו טומאה על ארץ העמים. gazru tumah
al eretz ha'amim. They said that the land of outside of ישראל
Israel is considered טמא tamei. because you don't know where non-Jews are
buried and they might be and therefore you have to assume that
the land is טמא. tamei. You know also that obviously it could
have a pretty serious impact about כהנים leaving ישראל. Israel. ועל כלי
זכוכית. v'al klei zechochis. And that glassware is considered fit to becoming
טמא. tamei. Because in the תורה Torah really it's only metal and
pottery you know and... and you know and leather and whatever other
types of things but not
glassware. Glassware... חז"ל Chazal tell us from when they first started making
glassware, when was it? Ancient. So okay so even though even in
the time of the תורה Torah glassware was around, but interestingly it's
not mentioned in the תורה Torah as something that can become טמא.
tamei, So here... so anyway here they said it can. So let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: והא רבנן
דשמונים שנה גזרו. ve'ha rabbanan d'shmonim shanah gazru.
One minute, the Rabbis from eighty years before the destruction of the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash made the גזירה, gezeirah the גזירה gezeirah. of...
we'll see... ארץ העמים eretz ha'amim not glassware. דאמר רב כהנא כשחלה
רבי ישמעאל בר רבי יוסי... de'amar Rav Kahana keshechala Rabbi Yishmael bar
Rabbi Yosei... When רבי ישמעאל בר רבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael bar Rabbi
Yosei got sick, שלחו לו... shalchu lo... so they sent to him:
רבי אמור לנו בי ג' דברים שאמרת לנו משום אביך. Rabbi, emor
lanu be-eizeh gimel devarim she'amarta lanu mishum avicha. Tell us two or
three sayings that you... that you know in the name of your
father. It's quite interesting here he's sick which usually means they're expecting
he might die. And you might say that they want to say
tell us two or three of your teachings, you're about to die,
we want to hold on to your תורה, Torah, but they say
tell us two or three things in your father's name.
So I understand they wanted—he was the last link to the father,
I understand—so they wanted to preserve what his father had taught, but
if there's somebody is dying, I think it'd probably be better to
hear you want to hear what I have, my teachings, rather my
father's teachings. Anyway, but that's what they did. They said tell us
two or three things in the name of your father. שלח להם,
Shalach lahem, he sent to them, כך אמר אבא, Kach amar Abba,
here's what my father said. Or maybe אדרבה, Adrabba, maybe it makes
him feel whatever good that he's, maybe also the message is your
father died and he's not forgotten, so maybe there's like a message
about that and we're still trying to hold on. Anyway, who knows?
Anyway, whatever the issue was in terms of the pastoral aspects, they
wanted to know what his father had said before he died. So
here's what my father said: קפ שנה עד שלא חרב הבית, Kaf-peish
shana ad shelo charav habayis, 180 years before the destruction of the
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, which is 70 in the common era, so
this is about 110 BCE, פשטה מלכות הרשעה על ישראל, Pashta malchus
ha'resha'ah al Yisrael, the evil kingdom spread over Israel, which means like
Rome, okay? So basically we were subject to Rome from about 110
BCE. פ שנה עד שלא חרב הבית, Peish shana ad shelo charav
habayis, 80 years before the destruction of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
which is about 10 BCE, גזרו טומאה על ארץ העמים, Gazru tumah
al eretz ha'amim, they said that the land of the non-Jews is
טמא. tamei. So again, that's 80 years before the
חורבן churban and על כלי זכוכית, v'al klei zechuchis, and on the
glassware. So exactly what we said was יוסי בן יועזר איש צרידה
ויוסי בן יוחנן איש ירושלים Yosei ben Yoezer ish Tzeredah v'Yosei ben
Yochanan ish Yerushalayim about the glassware and the land outside of Israel,
we're saying now was 80 years before the חורבן, churban, and we're
going to show that the dates don't match up. Well, let's see.
מ שנה עד שלא חרב הבית, Mem shana ad shelo charav habayis,
now 40 years before the חורבן הבית, churban habayis, about 30 of
the common era, גלתה לה סנהדרין, Galtah lah Sanhedrin, the סנהדרין Sanhedrin
left הר הבית, Har HaBayis, וישבה לה בחנויות, v'yashvah lah bechanuyos, and
dwelt in the stores, meaning somewhere
in ירושלים Yerushalayim but not on הר הבית. Har HaBayis. So the
גמרא Gemara says למאי הלכתא, l'mai hilchata, why is that relevant halachically?
אמר רב יצחק בר אבדימי, Amar Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi, לומר שלא
דנו דיני קנסות, lomar shelo danu dinei knasos, they were no longer
able to judge issues of fines. So the גמרא Gemara says דיני
קנסות סלקא דעתך, dinei knasos salka dach-tach, do you really mean that?
Why can't you judge fines if you're not on הר הבית? Har
HaBayis? As long as you have a בית דין Beis Din that
has סמיכה, semichah, you can judge fines. אלא אימא שלא דנו דיני
נפשות, Ela eima shelo danu dinei nefashos, they didn't deal with capital
cases. Now this actually, I should say parenthetically, תוספות Tosafos is very
bothered with this. תוספות Tosafos says the only place we find that
it matters that the בית דין Beis Din is actually sitting on
הר הבית Har HaBayis is by the זקן ממרא, Zaken Mamre, where
it says אל המקום אשר יבחר השם אלוקיך בו, el hamakom asher
yivchar Hashem Elokecha bo, מלמד שהמקום גורם, melamed shehamakom gorem,
it only can be on הר הבית. Har HaBayis. That's only when
their authority is being threatened by a זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre and
they're fully embodying their role as their authority because they're the בית
דין הגדול Beis Din HaGadol on הר הבית. Har HaBayis. Any other
time, but that's about
זקן ממרא. Zaken Mamre. זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre is the person who
rules against the בית דין הגדול Beis Din HaGadol and sets himself
up as a competing authority and he gets put to death. But
that's when they're embodying fully their role as authority and they're on
הר הבית. Har HaBayis. Otherwise you don't have the הלכה halacha of
זקן ממרא. Zaken Mamre. But otherwise תוספות Tosafos says we never find
by capital crimes it matters that you're in that there's dwelling in
הר הבית Har HaBayis or not. So תוספות Tosafos is very bothered
by this גמרא, Gemara he doesn't really have an answer. We'll just
note that as a footnote. Moving on though, the גמרא says like
this, so now we have that this גזירה gezeirah was made 80
years before the חורבן. churban. And we also have a teaching that
it was יוסי בן יועזר איש צרידה ויוסי בן יוחנן איש ירושלים.
Yosei ben Yoezer ish Tzeredah v'Yosei ben Yochanan ish Yerushalayim. וכי תימא,
V'chi teima, so now obviously the most obvious thing to suggest is
it's the same time. וכי תימא בפ שנה נמי אינהו הוו, V'chi
teima b'peish shana nami inhu havu, that they were 80 years before
the חורבן? churban? That can't be. והתניא, V'hatanya, we learned in a
ברייתא, Baraita, הלל ושמעון גמליאל ושמעון. Hillel v'Shimon Gamliel v'Shimon. So this
is the descendants of הלל. Hillel הלל, Hillel his son שמעון, Shimon,
גמליאל, Gamliel, and then his son שמעון. Shimon. So the last one
was רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. נהגו נשיאותן בפני
הבית מאה שנה, Nahagu nesi'usan bifnei habayis meiah shana, מאה שנה, meiah
shana, excuse me, מאה שנה. meiah shana. Those all those four generations
were 100 years before the חורבן. churban. So basically
what it's saying is הלל Hillel. started 100 years before the
חורבן. churban. ואילו יוסי בן יועזר איש צרידה ויוסי בן יוחנן, V'ilu
Yosei ben Yoezer ish Tzeredah v'Yosei ben Yochanan, we know the listing
of the generations in פרקי אבות Pirkei Avos were many generations before
הלל. Hillel So if הלל Hillel was 100 years before the חורבן,
churban, so then they were obviously much more than 100 years before
the חורבן. churban. So how can you say it was they that
did it if we have another version that it was done 80
years before the חורבן? churban? Without taking too much time, but just
to give you—if I pass this around, this is a wonderful book
which is like two volumes, I don't even remember the name, anyway,
a book about that shows all the תנאים Tannaim and the אמוראים.
Amoraim. So here's a listing of the generations of הלל. Hillel.
So if you take a look, we'll just look at this very
quickly, okay, he gives the whole list of הלל's Hillel, descendants and
these are the נשיאים. Nesi'im. So if הלל was 100 years before
the חורבן, Churban, it's 30 BCE. Then you have שמעון בן הלל,
Shimon ben Hillel, of whom we don't know too much. Then you
have right, it says הלל, שמעון, גמליאל, שמעון, Hillel, Shimon, Gamliel, Shimon,
right? So that's הלל, שמעון. Hillel, Shimon. רבן גמליאל הזקן Rabban Gamliel
ha-Zaken is the grandson of הלל. So he was the head of
בית הלל, okay, and that was the בית הלל. You had from
הלל to בית הלל. Okay, and a lot of the תקנות, takanos
תיקן רבן גמליאל tikken Rabban Gamliel that the עדים eidos would that
they would there were various תקנות takanos mentioned about him like the
עדים eidos for קידוש החודש kiddush hachodesh and about things that were
done לתיקון עולם. letikkun olam. So תיקן רבן גמליאל tikken Rabban Gamliel
comes up a number of times. That was רבן גמליאל הזקן, Rabban
Gamliel ha-Zaken, still when there was a בית המקדש. Beis ha-Mikdash. Then
you had רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, which was
at the time of, that's what Moshe said, those four generations got
you to חורבן הבית. Churban ha-Bayis. So he was the first generation
of תנאים, Tannaim, although obviously הלל and whatever רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
are mentioned, we normally count the generations of תנאים Tannaim starting at
the דור החורבן, dor ha-churban, okay, although obviously there were תנאים Tannaim
earlier. And he was one of the הרוגי מלכות Harugei Malchut actually.
Not the הרוגי מלכות Harugei Malchut of the Hadrianic persecutions of רבי
עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva time, but הרוגי מלכות Harugei Malchut during the חורבן.
churban. The עשרה הרוגי מלכות Asarah Harugei Malchut did not all occur
at the same time. Okay, then just to look after the חורבן,
churban, you had רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel of יבנה, Yavne, right, once
now you no longer have a בית המקדש, Beis ha-Mikdash, you had
יבנה. Yavne. And this is the סתם stam רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
is not רבן גמליאל הזקן, Rabban Gamliel ha-Zaken, it's the רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel of יבנה. Yavne. He was the one you might remember
that had all those clashes with רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, right, and
he sort of exerted his authority over רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, and
we had that whole גמרא right about him getting deposed for a
while. So all those stories about that, that was all with רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel of יבנה, Yavne, and then that was roughly around
the time, then after him, the third generation was the period of
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, and then רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel the second was a contemporary of the תלמידי רבי עקיבא
talmidei Rabbi Akiva like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda and so on. And then רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda ha-Nasi,
that's 200 CE, and that's the end of the משנה. So this
gives you a certain sense of, and we were talking about the
four generations up to חורבן הבית, Churban ha-Bayis, yes.
I'm missing a נשיא Nasi there is
רבן יוחנן בן זכאי. Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai.
Right, I mean he was not from, right, he was not from
the family of הלל. This is the list of the family of
הלל, right. Okay, anyway, so now we have, so now we have
this question, so let's turn to טו עמוד ב. Tes-Vov amud Beis.
So was it 80 years before the חורבן churban or was it
much earlier, this issue about ארץ העמים eretz ha-ammim and the glassware?
So the גמרא says it's going to ignore the glassware for now
and focus on the ארץ העמים, eretz ha-ammim, and here's what it
says: אלא אתו אינהו גזרו אגושה. Ella atu inhu gazru agusha.
Fine, like Michael suggested, like we saw before, well, actually, you're jumping
to the second answer. But the first answer is we try to
do it in stages. So they said when they were the יוסי
בן יועזר Yose ben Yoezer etc., they said that what would be
the problem? The actual גוש gush of ארץ העמים, eretz ha-ammim, לשרוף,
lisrof, that if you actually touch the ground you would be considered
totally טמא, tamei and if you touch תרומה terumah you'd burn the
תרומה. terumah, So the ואוירא ולא כלום. ve-avira velo klum. So there
are two degrees of stages we can go here with this טומאה.
tumah Number one is the ground versus the air. If somebody is
traveling in the airspace and never touches the ground, if you're assuming
that there are dead bodies buried somewhere, then if you're over them,
even if you're not touching the ground, you're also טמא. tamei? But
let's say, but that was a second level גזירה. gezeirah Even though
it's all true, I mean if you really think there are dead
bodies, then if you're in the airspace, obviously you're טמא tamei as
well, although not necessarily. תוספות Tosafot points out non-Jews are not necessarily
מטמא באהל. metamei be-ohel. There's a debate of תנאים Tannaim about that,
so that might also be what's part of it. So the first
level גזירה gezeirah was touching the ground. There was a second level
גזירה gezeirah. or second way in which the גזירה gezeirah could have
applied, which is even in the airspace without touching the ground. That's
one way in which it could work in stages. Do we apply
it to the airspace? The second way to work in stages is
what happens if you become טמא? tamei Are you considered so טמא
tamei. that if you touch תרומה terumah you burn it? Or טמא
tamei. enough that if you touch תרומה terumah you can't eat the
תרומה, terumah. but you don't burn it as well unless it decomposes
and so on. So this is how we're going to try to
say that there were stages of the גזירה. gezeira So that the
earliest stage, גזרו אגושה לשרוף, gazru agusha lisrof, if you touch the
ground you would burn תרומה, terumah ואוירא ולא כלום ve-avira velo klum
and nothing about the air. גזרו רבנן דפישא gazru rabanan de-pisha and
the ones that were 80 years before the חורבן, churban, גזרו אוירא
לתלות. gazru avira litlos. And they said they would, they said no,
air also, not that you would burn, but that you would suspend
תרומה. terumah. So the גמרא says, למימרא דחדא גזירתא הויא לשריפה? le-memra
de-chada gezeirata hava lishreifa?
Are you telling me that you immediately made the גזירה gezeirah to
burn by the ground? ואמר אילפא, ve-amar Ilfa, but אילפא Ilfa says,
ידים, when it came to the hands, this is like what we
talked about before, when it came to the טומאה tumah, of the
hands, תחילה גזירתם לשריפה. techillas gezeirasam lishreifa.
From the very outset they said if your hands touch תרומה terumah,
you burn it. So the גמרא's going to make a דיוק, diyuk,
ידים הוא. yadayim hu.
By the hands we say the very immediately they said if you
touch תרומה terumah you burn it. הא מידי אחריני, Ha midi achrini,
other things that they said you were going to treat as a
שני, sheni, as problematic for תרומה, terumah. לא, that presumably went in
stages, the initially they said don't eat the תרומה terumah, don't burn
it and only in a second stage they said burn it. אלא,
ela, okay let's try it this way then. אטו אינהו גזרו אגושא
לטרוס ואויר לא כלום? Atu innu gazru agusha litros ve'avir lo klum?
Fine, this is easy. We'll say fine, the first גזירה gezeirah was
if you touch the ground you suspend the תרומה terumah. and the
air space you do nothing. ועשו רבנן דתשעים שנה, Va'asu rabbanan detish'im
shana, the second stage was the Rabbis of eighty years before the
חורבן, churban, גזרו אגושא לשרוף, gazru agusha lisrof, that's now as a
second stage we say if you touch the ground now you'll burn
it, this was a later development, ואוירא לטלוס ve'avira litlos and the
air to be suspended. Okay, doesn't matter we can say it in
stages, we'll say the stages a little differently. The first stage was
just if you touch just the ground and just to suspend תרומה.
Terumah The second stage was if you touch the ground you burn
the תרומה Terumah. and the air you suspend.
And was יוסי בן יועזר Yosi ben Yoezer that first stage?
Yes, the first stage was יוסי בן יועזר. Yosi ben Yoezer. So
the גמרא says והא קאיתא באושא גזרו? ve'ka ite biUsha gazru? Wait
one minute, that doesn't work because we have we say that this
idea of ארץ העמים Eretz Ha'amim was in אושא. Usha. אושא Usha
was right after the חורבן. churban. Okay, so that's obviously the last
part, later than these two stages. דתנן, Detnan, we taught in the
משנה, על שש ספיקות שורפין את התרומה. Al shesh sefeikos sorfin es
haterumah. For six reasons you burn תרומה. Terumah. So this is again
like things that are like a שני לטומאה, sheni letumah and we
are going to assume by the way that these six although the
things we mentioned before about שני לטומאה sheni letumah were about בית
שמאי ובית הלל Beis Shammai veBeis Hillel where the eighteen, these that
we're mentioning that are also a list about things that are שני
לטומאה sheni letumah. are assumed to have taken place in אושא Usha
at תקנת אושא Takanas Usha after the חורבן הבית. Churban HaBayis. It's
pretty amazing right how many גזירות gezeiros and תקנות there were about
things that were שני לטומאה sheni letumah and were a problem for
תרומה, Terumah. really shows you how central again טומאה וטהרה tumah vetaharah,
was to their religious
life. So בית שמאי ובית הלל Beis Shammai veBeis Hillel had their
eighteen things, a lot of them were about being שני לטומאה. sheni
letumah, Now we have another list of things that are שני לטומאה
sheni letumah. and make a problem for תרומה Terumah. which were later
than them, which were at חורבן churban after חורבן הבית Churban HaBayis
at אושא. Usha. One minute, what are they? על ספק בית הפרס
Al sefek Beis HaPras about the doubt that remains a בית הפרס.
Beis HaPras. A בית הפרס Beis HaPras is a place that a
grave was plowed through so anywhere you walk there might be a
little chip of bone that that's only a rabbinic concern. ועל ספק
עפר הבא מארץ העמים, Ve'al sefek afar haba me'eretz ha'amim,
if you bring dirt, import, not only when you go to חוץ
לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, if you import dirt from חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz,
the dirt of חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz is considered to have a
doubtful טומאה because it might have little pieces of bone in it
or something. ועל ספק בגדי עם הארץ, Ve'al sefek bigdei am ha'aretz,
doubts about issues about the clothes of an עם הארץ. am ha'aretz.
Again this has to do with the general assumption that the עם
הארץ am ha'aretz as opposed to the rabbinic class were not careful
about טומאה וטהרה. So therefore they're not careful about טומאה וטהרה, they
might be a זב zav for all we know, the guy might
be a זב zav and he wouldn't have bothered going to the
מקווה mikvah or anything and therefore you have to be concerned that
his clothes are טמא. tamei Okay, and maybe his wife is a
נדה niddah is also a related concern. Okay. ועל ספק כלים הנמצאים.
Ve'al sefek keilim hanimtza'im.
How about if you just find random vessels you know and you
don't know what their provenance is so you have to be concerned
that they might be טמא. tamei. Okay. ועל ספק הרוקין, Ve'al sefek
harokin, as you see spit, now you have to be concerned because
it might be the spit of a זב zav or זבה zavah
or a נדה. niddah. Doesn't it make a difference
רשות הרבים reshus harabbim or
not and don't we have...
Not for this no. So this is that's a good point, in
general it might although we'll see in a minute hold on for
that but anyway this is all rabbinic anyway. Okay. Biblically these would
not be concerns, rabbinically these are where we are being מחמיר machmir
on all of this and we are saying that you have to
burn תרומה. So by the way I should say I said before
שני לטומאה, sheni l'tumah, this is not necessarily שני sheni. לטומאה. The
בית שמאי ובית הלל Beis Shammai veBeis Hillel were all about things
that are שני. Here though some of these things if we're really
concerned that the spit is from a זב, zav, it would be
an אב av and you would be a ראשון. rishon. But the
point here is not
the point here of שורפין sorfin is we're so concerned with it,
we're so strict on our rabbinic תקנה that we're not going to
say just suspend the תרומה, we're going to say really treat yourself
as really טמא tamei, and burn the תרומה. Okay. ועל ספק מי
רגלי אדם שכנגד מי רגלי בהמה Ve'al sefek mei raglei adam shekeneged
mei רגלי בהמה
and a doubt about human urine next to animal urine. Now what
does that mean? So the human urine is the same concern as
the spit that it might be from a זב zav or so
on and the why does it say next to animal urine? So
רש"י ותוספות Rashi veTosafos debate this. רש"י Rashi says even if there's
a real doubt whether it's human urine or not, meaning the other
stuff we knew what it was, we knew it was human spit,
we just didn't know whether it came from a זב zav or
not. Here there's a good reason to think it's right next to
animal urine, maybe it's human, maybe it's animal urine. Nevertheless even if
there's a doubt if it's human urine you have to be מחמיר.
machmir. So you understand it's different. All the other things you knew
what it was, you just didn't know if it was טמא. tamei.
Here even if you don't know what it was, even if only
maybe it's human urine you have to be מחמיר. machmir. תוספות Tosafos
says the exact opposite. This is no. We're saying next to animal
urine because if it's urine on its own you can assume it's
animal urine, but when it's side by side with animal urine then
it's clear there's a difference and you can see the difference, and
then you know it's human urine and only then you have to
be concerned. So תוספות Tosafos says the exact opposite of רש"י, Rashi,
that it's only when you're certain it's human urine. Anyway, these are
six things
where some ספק safek
that it might come from a זב, zav, the doubt is it
might be ספק
מי רגלי אדם במי רגלי בהמה. safek mei raglei adam be'mei raglei
beheima.
Right, like we said, ספק בגדי עם הארץ safek bigdei am ha'aretz
meaning it's not a question of what it is, you know it's
human urine, the question is whether it's טמא, tamei, the doubt is
whether it is טמא. tamei. Yeah.
No, no, they're not. No, no. Not moral.
No, no. It's ritual. So anyway, so the גמרא says, so these
are six things again that I misstated before, it's not שני לטומאה,
the reason of emphasizing תרומה is these are things that are possibly
an אבי אבות הטומאה. avi avos hatumah. Okay, but the issue here
is, although it's only a רבנן Rabbanan concern, we're going to be
so strict that it says you burn תרומה. So now we go
on to the issue about רשות הרבים reshus harabbim and רשות היחיד.
reshus hayachid ודאי מגען וספק טומאתן, vadai magaan v'safek tumasan,
all these things is when you definitely touched it, but you don't
know whether it was טמא, tamei, you don't know what its status
was. שורפין את התרומה, sorfin es ha'terumah, then you burn the תרומה.
You definitely touched it, we're going to treat them as definitely טמא.
tamei רבי יוסי אומר אף על ספק מגען, Rabbi Yossi omer af
al safek magaan, if you don't know if you touched it, that's
when רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, and רשות הרבים reshus harabbim makes a
difference. ברשות היחיד שורפין. bi'reshus hayachid sorfin. If it's in a רשות
היחיד, you treat it as if you definitely touched it. וחכמים אומרים
ברשות היחיד תולין ברשות הרבים טהור. vachachamim omrim bi'reshus hayachid tolin bi'reshus
harabbim tahor. No, even in a,
if it's a doubt if you touched it, even if it's in
a private domain, because there's (A) a doubt what its identity is
and (B) a doubt whether you touched it, so if you have
a double doubt, even in a private domain, we will say don't
burn, but in a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim it'll be totally טהור.
tahor. Right, because we're not going to go on a ספק. safek.
Because you're... okay anyway. So this raises general interesting questions of what's
the general rule of ספק טומאה ברשות היחיד. safek tumah b'reshus hayachid.
Is it only when there's a doubt if it was touched, or
is it even in a case when there's a doubt what its
identity was? Okay, but without getting into that more general question, anyway,
here the basic point clearly is that they made these things to
say שורפין את התרומה, sorfin es ha'terumah, and one of them was
ארץ העמים. eretz ha'amim. So when did they make this גזירה gezeirah.
of ארץ העמים? eretz ha'amim? So it says, now how do you
know this was אושא? Usha? Because באמר עולא, ba'amar Ulla, עולא Ulla
says, אלו ו' ספקות באושא התקינו. eilu vav sfekos b'Usha hitkinu.
These six things were all established in אושא. Usha. So now in
אושא Usha they said all these six things about urine and clothes
and ארץ העמים, eretz ha'amim, all these things we have to treat
as a ספק טומאה safek tumah so much that you would burn
תרומה. So what was אושא, Usha, which was at חורבן הבית, Churban
HaBayis, or was it 80 years before the חורבן? Churban? When did
we make this גזירה about ארץ העמים? eretz ha'amim? So the גמרא
is now going to have three stages to the גזירה. אלא, here's
what it is. עשו אינהו גזרו אגושה ליתלו ובאוויר ולא כלום. asu
inhu gazru a-gusha litlo u-v'avir v'lo khlum. So the first thing by
יוסי בן יועזר Yossi ben Yoezer was, if you touch the גוש,
gush, the ground, then you suspend ליתלו, litlo, and the אויר, avir,
the air, was nothing. ואתו רבנן דשמונים שנה גזרו איידי ואיידי ליתלו.
va'asu Rabbanan d'shmonim shanah gazru aidi v'aidi litlo. They said, they added
the air; the ground you suspend, and also the air you suspend.
But at this stage, we're only about the suspend, because the emphasis
of אושא, Usha, what was the emphasis of the תקנה of אושא?
Usha? The six things you're שורפין את התרומה. sorfin es ha'terumah. The
emphasis was not just to say you're טמא, tamei the emphasis was
to say you're so טמא tamei? that you're going to burn. So
we're going to leave that stage for the אושא Usha stage. ואתו
באושא גזרו אגושה לשרוף, va'asu b'Usha gazru a-gusha lisrof, you'll burn if
you touch the ground, ואוירא כדקאי קאי, v'avira k'dikay kay, and the
air will remain that if the air of ארץ העמים, eretz ha'amim,
it's תולין. tolin. So you've got it, we get these two stages
that preceded אושא. Usha. It's clear by אושא, Usha, the things that
they added to their list were things that are so טמא tamei,
or so much we're going to be strict about them that you
have to burn תרומה. So fine, we'll leave the burning to אושא.
Usha. So we've got to get two stages before אושא Usha that's
not about burning. So the first stage is the גוש gush you
suspend, אויר avir nothing. The next stage is גוש gush you suspend,
אויר avir you suspend. And comes אושא Usha and says the גוש
gush you burn and the אויר avir remains the way it was.
Okay, that was about ארץ העמים. eretz ha'amim. Now we move on
to the glassware. Let's just try to get started on this. כלי
זכוכית, klei zechuchis, what if you're just okay with a few more
minutes because we started very late. כלי זכוכית מאי טעמא גזרו בה
רבנן? klei zechuchis mai taama gazru bah Rabbanan?
Why did they treat glassware as טמא? tamei, So טומאה, if it's
not in the תורה. Torah. אמר רבי יוחנן אמר ריש לקיש, amar
Rabbi Yochanan amar Reish Lakish, הואיל ותחילת ברייתן מן החול, ho'il u'techilas
bri'asan min hachol, since glass is made from sand, שוויוהו רבנן ככלי
חרס, shavyuhu Rabbanan k'klei cheres, they made it like pottery. Pottery comes
from dirt, glass comes from sand, so they treated it like pottery,
and therefore if pottery can be מקבל טומאה, mekabbel tumah, they said
רבנן rabbananly the same with glass. So the גמרא says, אלא מעתה
לא תהא להם טהרה במקוה. ela me'ata lo tehei lahem tahara b'mikveh.
If it's like pottery, so pottery you can't put into a מקוה
mikveh to make it טהור. tahor. Pottery, the way you make it
טהור tahor is you have to break it. So if glass we're
going to treat like a type of a pottery, why do we
allow you to make it טהור tahor in a מקוה? mikveh? How
do we know we allow you to do this? אלמה תנן, almah
tnan, why do we teach: ואלו חוצצין בכלים. ve'eilu chotzetzin b'keilim.
The following things is a חציצה, chatzitza, right, an impediment to dunking
it in the מקוה. mikveh. What are they? הזפת והמור בכלי זכוכית.
Hazefet vehamor bikli zechuchit.
Tar and מור, mor, which I assume is myrrh, which is
in glassware. So anyway there are these types of things that are
adhesive even to glass and are a problem if you put it
in the מקוה. mikveh. But the basic point is it shows you
can put glass into a מקוה mikveh and make it טהור. tahor.
Okay, this is not the same as when we took our glassware
and put it in the מקוה mikveh when we do טבילת כלים.
tevilat kelim. That's a different thing, you know when it's but anyway
when it really became טמא, tamei. you could put it into a
מקוה. mikveh. So why is it if you're going to treat it
like pottery? So the גמרא says no, this is a special case
when you put it in a מקוה. mikveh. What's the case? הכא
במאי עסקינן כגון שניקבו. Hacha bemai askinan kegon shenikbu. There was a
hole in the glass והטיף לתוכן אבר vehetif letochan avar and you
filled the hole with lead. By the way, a lot of people
died in the ancient world because of lead poisoning. Okay, anyway, so
you filled this hole with lead. ורבי מאיר היא, VeRabbi Meir hi,
and it's Rabbi Meir דאמר de'amar הכל הולך אחר המעמיד. hakol holech
achar hama'amid.
Things are defined by the something that gives it sort of stands
it, that gives it structure, that makes it function. So because this
thing can only is fixed by lead, it changes its identity. It
got a hole in it, so if it were if it were
pottery, pottery with a hole in it stops being a כלי, keli,
a vessel. Right? Yes. So when it got the hole, it stopped
being a vessel. What made it a vessel? That you filled it
with lead. So now the it's now defined as a lead vessel.
It was not a vessel as glass as pottery, it had a
hole, what returned it into a vessel was the lead, now it's
like a metal vessel. In this case, because it's like a metal
vessel, you can put it in the מקוה, mikveh, but if it
were only a normal glass vessel you could not. Okay, and let's
just see the Rabbi Meir and we'll end with that. How do
you know Rabbi Meir says that? דתניא, Detanya, כלי זכוכית שניקבו, kli
zechuchit shenikbu,
if you have a glass vessel that got a hole והטיף לתוכן
אבר vehetif letochan avar and you put and you filled it with
lead. So אמר רבי שמעון בן גמליאל רבי מאיר מטמא וחכמים מטהרין.
Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel Rabbi Meir metamei vechachamim mitaherin. That
in that case, Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel says Rabbi Meir would say
it's טמא, tamei חכמים say it's טהור. tahor. So presumably again this
means it's there's many ways to describe that debate, but the way
the גמרא is understanding it is that Rabbi Meir says it now
has become a vessel and what type of a vessel? A metal
vessel. וחכמים say no, it is not טמא. tamei Now תוספות Tosafot
asks, well, let it be at least טמא tamei like a glass
vessel, don't call it a metal vessel, call it a glass vessel.
So the answer might be maybe yes, but anyway that would be
only רבנן. rabbanan. But only Rabbi Meir says it's really fully a
metal vessel and therefore can it become טמא even דאורייתא, de'oraita, biblically.
So when would we say glass you can put to the מקוה?
mikveh? If it was a hole filled with lead. But the normal
assumption that we're saying here, we'll revisit this tomorrow, is that glass
is a type of a pottery vessel except in a very special
case, and if it's a type of a pottery vessel it can
become טמא in certain ways, but you cannot make it טהור tahor
in a מקוה. mikveh. And we will continue this tomorrow.